# Dr. M. Usman Maqbool **Bhutta**

□ (+852) 609-44-786 | wsmanmaqbool@outlook.com | # usmanmaqbool.github.io | wsmanmaqbool | wsmanmaqbool | wsmanmaqbool

"Roboticist"

### Summary.

With the rise of autonomous systems, being a researcher and entrepreneur, my research direction is their deployment to the real world. For any autonomous mode of the robot, a 3D map is essential to navigate and operate at any place. I work to tackle the problems related to scale difference and loop closures for large scale 3D mapping. I've 7+ years of experience specializing in robotics R&D and project management. I previously owned an IT company, and I've been part of several startups since 2011. My full profile can view here (https://usmanmaqbool.github.io/).

## Work Experience [7+ Years]

RESEARCH (COMPUTER VISION TECHNOLOGIES AND ROBOTICS SYSTEM)

#### Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab, Robotics Institute

**HKUST**, HK

РнD

Sep 2016 - Feb 2021 PhD Supervisor: Prof Ming Liu, Director of Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab (RAM-LAB)

- **Research Contributions as First Author**
- Place Recognition: Our work makes a leap towards hierarchical deep learning-based place recognition for multiagent SLAM systems. We introduce a probabilistic layer to constrain the local representation along with the global representation of images. The global description of the pre-trained model and the local consistency introduced in our work enables the system to yield good performance at large-scale. Development Using: MATLAB, Python, Jupyter, Nvidia CUDA, Docker, Deep learning, Matconvnet

Multi-Agent SLAM: I've produced Loop-box for the multi-Agent Direct SLAM Triggered by Single Loop Closure for Large scale semi dense 3D reconstruction /large-scale structure from motion. This work is accepted for publication in IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics (IF= 11+)... Development using: C++ 11, ROS, OpenCV, OpenGV, Paraview, EVO, UGV, LSD-SLAM, Monocular Camera.

SLAM: I've worked mainly for the multi-agent SLAM system. To find the scale difference and excellent relative transformation between difference agents. I've produced PCR-Pro work. This work got best student paper finalist award at IEEE-CYBER 2018.

Development using: C++ 11, ROS, OpenCV, OpenGV, Paraview, EVO, Monocular Camera, Plotly

Automation (Inspection): For smartphone glass inspection, I've introduced Smart-Inspect work. This work is accepted in IROS 2020. The patent is also under-review in the US.

Development using: Python, Jupyter, Nvidia CUDA, K-Means, Docker, Machine learning (ML)

#### Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL)

ETH Zürich, Switzerland.

ACADEMIC GUEST

Oct. 2019 - Mar. 2020

- Supervisor: Prof. Roland Siegwart, Director of Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL), ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Co-Supervisor: Dr. Cesar Dario Cadena Lerma, Senior Researcher at ASL, ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Research in Place Recognition: I've worked for making the better place recognition for the better scene understanding. Furthermore, I've also introduced light weight representation of key-frames for better channel utilization.

Development using: MATLAB, Python, Jupyter, Nvidia CUDA, Docker, Deep learning, Matconvnet

#### **Department of Electronics**

**QAU**, Pakistan Mar. 2010 - Jun. 2012

• M.Phil. Supervisor: **Prof Hasan Mahmood**, Department of Electronics, QAU.

Research in Image Processing (CNN): I've introduced CNN-based license plate recognition of Pakistani's Cars. This work has been published in IEEE-ICALIP 2014.

#### INDUSTRY AND ENTREPRENEURSHIP

#### **Lisee Technology Corporation Limited**

Central. HK

Jan 2018 - Jan 2021

- Won funding support for company | TSSSU Support HK\$ 300,000 (Jun 19 - May 20).

- Indoor Navigation for Libray using Lisee Technology | PCF Support HK\$ 160,000 (Jun 18 - May 19).

#### **Friends Corporate Technologies**

Islamabad, PK Feb 2013 - Aug 2015

50+ Projects | Electronics/ Electrical Engineering, R&D, image processing, Web Applications Development, MVC Applications

#### **Federal Government of Pakistan**

**Islamabad**, PK

coo

May 2012 - Feb 2013

Electronics/ Electrical Engineering, R&D, image processing

#### Server4Sale, LLC

**Islamabad**, PK Dec 2009 - Mar 2010

1

PHP DEVELOPER

Php web application development for Joomla and Zend frameworks.

#### **ACADEMIC**

**Department of Computer Science** 

**BZU-Sahiwal**, Pakistan

Feb 2016 - Jun 2016

Oct. 2015 - May. 2016

LECTURER (VISITING)

Teaching MCS and BS-CS courses

**Department of Physics** 

**GPGC** Sahiwal, Pakistan

CTI

Teaching BS physics (Electronics related courses + Labs + Projects)

**Department of Electronics** 

**QAU**, Pakistan

Aug. 2010 - Dec. 2010

'PHP Web Development' (a short course) offered in Department of Electronics, Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan.

### **Education**

#### Ph.D. in Robotics and AI at RAM-LAB, Robotics Institute

**HKUST**, Hong Kong

DEPARTMENT OF ELECTRONIC & COMPUTER ENGINEERING, THE HONG KONG UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY

Sep. 2016 - Feb. 2021

- PhD Supervisor: Prof Ming Liu, Director of Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab (RAM-LAB)
- Exchange Supervisor: Prof. Roland Siegwart, Director of Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL), ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Exchange Co-Supervisor: Dr. Cesar Dario Cadena Lerma, Senior Researcher at ASL, ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Got PEEF CCMS PhD scholarship from Pakistan and overseas research award (ORA).
- Research: Multi-Agent SLAM System, Place Recognition, Autonomous Car and Deep Learning for automation industry. Hand on experience on RGB-D 3D recontruction, Multi-view stereo, python and C++ development experience, multi-threaded coding.3D mesh registration, paraview and parameterizations. Moreover, I've deep understanding of data structures and algorithms. Experience with software development on Linux open-source stack. Calculus, linear algebra and geometry related courses have been taken.

M.Phil. in Electronics **OAU**, Pakistan

DEPARTMENT OF ELECTRONICS, QUAID-I-AZAM UNIVERSITY, ISLAMABAD, PAKISTAN.

Mar. 2010 - Jun. 2012

- M.Phil. Supervisor: Prof Hasan Mahmood, Department of Electronics, QAU.
- Research: Signal and Image Processing
- Grade: A

M.Sc. in Electronics **OAU**, Pakistan

DEPARTMENT OF ELECTRONICS, QUAID-I-AZAM UNIVERSITY, ISLAMABAD, PAKISTAN.

Mar. 2010 - Jun. 2012

- 2nd position in batch
- Projects: completed 9+ projects related to C++, Verilog/HDL and Micro-controller programming.

#### **B.Sc. in Mathematics and Physics**

**BZU**. Pakistan

BAHAUDDIN ZAKARIYA UNIVERSITY, MULTAN PAKISTAN

Mar. 2010 - Jun. 2012

· Grade: 1st Division

## **Presentation**

#### IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems [IROS, 2020]

Las Vegas, USA

PRESENTOR AS AUTHOR

PRESENTOR AS AUTHOR

Oct. 2020

• Introduced Smart-Inspect for the micro scale localization and classification of smartphone glass defects for industrial automation.

#### **Technology Start-up Support Scheme for Universities (TSSSU)**

HKUST, Hong Kong Jan. 2019

PRESENTER AS COO LISEE TECHNOLOGY CORPORATION COMPANY LIMITED, HONG KONG.

Introduced Lisee technology in front of selection committee panel and won TSSSU 2019-20 funding of the amount of HK\$300,000.

#### IEEE Int. Conf. on CYBER Technology in Automation, Control, and Intelligent Systems [IEEE-CYBER 2018]

Tianjin, China

Introduced PCR-Pro for the estimation of information matrix and scale difference for pose graph SLAM.

#### IET-Young Professionals Exhibition and Competition (IET-YPEC) 2018

CityU, Hong Kong

PRESENTER AS COO LISEE TECHNOLOGY CORPORATION COMPANY LIMITED, HONG KONG.

Jul. 2018

Jul. 2018

• Introduced Lisee technology at IET-YPEC 2018.

#### **Campus Challenge @ HKUST Transportation**

HKUST, Hong Kong

PRESENTER AS PARTICIPENT

May 2018

• HKUST got 80+ proposals for this compeitions, and arranged a roadshow. My proposal got selected for the audiance award after getting maximum votes.

#### **High Tech Innovation and Entrepreneurship**

PRESENTER AS ENTREPRENEUR

• Introduced my study related to the flying cars.

HKUST, Hong Kong

Dec. 2017

#### **World First Youth Robotics Developemnt Forum 2017**

Shangri-La Shenzhen, China.

Nov. 2017

Islamabad, PK

Mansehra, PK

Islamabad, PK

Islamabad, PK

3

• Introduced my work related to multi-agent SLAM system.

### Honors & Awards \_\_\_\_\_

#### INTERNATIONAL

PRESENTER AS AUTHOR.

July, 2018	Intelligent Systems	Tianjin, China	
May, 2018	Audience Award, Campus Challenge - Transportation, HKUST	HKUST, HK	
Nov, 2017	Best Mapper Award, Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab, HKUST	Shenzhen, China	
May, 2017	Completion Award, The Graduate Teaching Assistant Training, HKUST	HKUST, HK	
Dec, 2016	Best External Award, Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab, HKUST	Shenzhen, China	
Nov, 2016	Completion Award, Author Workshop, Elsevier Publishing Campus	HKUST, HK	
Domestic			
Sep 2016	CCMS PhD Scholarship, Won Chief Minister Marit Scholarship (CCMS) scholarship award by Punjab Government (PEEF), Pakistan for pursuing my PhD studies at HKUST, HK	Lahore, PK	
Sep 2013	<b>Participant</b> , Painting for peace (Pakistan-India-Afghanistan) event, a part of the Harmony initiative	Islamabad, PK	
Apr 2013	Participant, Case Spark in business plan competition	Islamabad, PK	
Apr 2013	Participant, Case EPICA	Islamabad, PK	
Apr 2013	Participant, How to be a Better Playwright Workshop by PNCA and US Embassay Pakistan	Islamabad, PK	
Oct 2012	Participant, Punjab Youth Festival	Lahore, PK	
Oct 2011	Participant, Int'l Youth Conference and Festival	Islamabad, PK	
Sep 2011	Participant, Asian Youth Conference and Peace Festival	Lahore, PK	
Apr 2011	<b>Completion Award</b> , Acting and Directing Theater Workshop by PNCA and US Embassay Pakistan	Islamabad, PK	
Dec 2011	Participant, National Drama Festival	Islamabad, PK	

Best Student Paper Finalist Award, IEEE Int. Conf. on CYBER Technology in Automation, Control, and

Dec 2010 Instuctor of short Course, PHP Web Development' at the Department of Electronics, QAU

Apr 2013 Completion Award, Running River Rafting course by Adventure Foundation of Pakistan

Dec 2008 Award of Honor, Finance Secretary of Electronics Student Society (ESS) at QAU

Apr 2013 Completion Award, Paragliding course by QAU Adventure Club

#### Academic Activities \_\_\_\_\_

ICRA IROS	Referee Service, IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Robotics and Automation Referee Service, IEEE/RSJ RA-L and International Conference on Robotics and Automation	2021, -20 2021,-20, -19, -18
HKUST, HK <b>Teaching Assistant</b> , EESM 5547 - Multimedia Signal Processing		Spr 2020, Spr 2019, Spr 2018
CASE	Referee Service, IEEE International Conference on Automation Science and Engineering	2019
HKUST, HK <b>Teaching Assistant</b> , ELEC4820 - Medical Imaging		Fall 2018
HKUST, HK <b>Teaching Assistant</b> , ELEC 1010 - Electronic and Information Technology		Spr 2017

#### Skills\_\_\_\_\_

Robotics and Computer Vision Ubuntu, ROS, PCL, Docker, Catkin, OpenCV, OpenGV, Ceres Solver, g2o, Libpointmatcher Machine Learning / Deep Learning Jupyter, Pytorch, Tensorflow, Keras, CUDA **Programming** Python, C/C++, Matlab, git, LaTeX, FPGA, Verilog Web mkdocs, Hugo, Jekyll, PHP, MYSQL **Languages** English, Urdu

### Research Publications

## Why-So-Deep: Image Correspondence Verification by Probabilistic Spatial Landmarks Elevation for Visual Place Recognition

M USMAN MAQBOOL BHUTTA\*, YUXIANG SUN AND MING LIU

The IEEE Transactions on Automation Science and Engineering (T-ASE)

Submitted

Journal Paper

## Loop-box: Multi-Agent Direct SLAM Triggered by Single Loop Closure for Large Scale Mapping

Journal Paper

Oct 2020

 $\hbox{M Usman Maqbool Bhutta$^*$, Manohar Kuse, Rui Fan, Yanan Liu and Ming Liu}$ 

IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics (IF: 11+)

Smart-Inspect: Micro Scale Localization and Classification of Smart Phone Glass Defects for Industrial Automation

Conference Paper

M Usman Maqbool Bhutta\*, Shoaib Aslam, Peng Yun, Jianhao JiAO and Ming Liu

Oct 2020

IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS 2020)

Multiple Lane Detection Algorithm Based on Optimised Dense Disparity Map Estimation

Conference Paper

Han Ma, Yixin Ma, Jianhao Jiao, M Usman Maqbool Bhutta, Mohammud Junaid Bocus, Lujia Wang, Ming Liu and Rui

Dec 2018

Accepted in IEEE International Conference on Imaging Systems and Techniques (IST 2018)

## PCR-Pro: 3D Sparse and Different Scale Point Clouds Registration and Robust Estimation of Information Matrix For Pose Graph SLAM

Conference Paper

Jul 2018

Presented in IEEE Int. Conf. on CYBER Technology in Automation, Control, and Intelligent Systems (IEEE-CYBER 2018), and won Best Student Paper Finalist Award.

## An intelligent approach for robust detection and recognition of multiple color and font styles automobiles license plates: A feature-based algorithm

Conference Paper

M Usman Maqbool Bhutta\*, Hasan Mahmood, and Haroon Malik

Jan 2015

Published in IEEE International Conference on Audio, Language and Image Processing (ICALIP 2014).

#### Efficient Reset Design Techniques

M USMAN MAQBOOL BHUTTA\* AND MING LIU

Journal Paper

QAMAR, ZOHA, BUSHRA YASEEN, AND USMAN MAQBOOL

2015

Published in Science International Lahore

#### **Patent**

#### Semi-Supervised Learning Approach for Smart Phone Glasses Defect Inspection

US Patent

Muhammad Usman Maqbool Bhutta, Jianhao Jiao, Peng Yun, Yuan Wang, Xuebin Sun, Ming Liu

Jan 2020

TTC.PA.1315, US Provisional Patent Application (No. 62/974,937).

#### References

#### **Prof Ming Liu**

Ph.D. Supervisor

ASSOCIATE PROFESSOR · DIRECTOR OF ROBOTICS AND MULTI-PERCEPTION LAB (RAM-LAB), DEPARTMENT OF ELECTRONIC AND COMPUTER ENGINNEERING, HKUST, HK.

eelium@ust.hk

(+852) 2358 7058

#### Dr. Cesar Dario Cadena Lerma

Exchange Co-Supervisor

Senior Researcher  $\,\cdot\,$  ASL, ETH Zürich, Switzerland

cesarcadena.lerma@gmail.com

(+41) (0)44 633-8803

**Prof. Hasan Mahmood** 

#### M.Phil. Supervisor

PROFESSOR · CHAIRPERSON, DEPARTMENT OF ELECTRONICS, QAU, ISLAMABAD, PAKISTAN.

hasan@gau.edu.pk

(+92) (0)51 9064 3132